# David J. Filipiak

108 Meadow View Drive • Wethersfield, CT 06109 • Cell: (860)335-4122 • djf224@cornell.edu

## **PROFILE**

Experienced and professional biomedical engineer with a proven track record of exceptional project leadership and management. Possesses a diverse skillset including computational modeling and analysis resulting in increased output efficiency, decreased cost, and design validation. <u>Core competencies include</u>:

Product Design & DevelopmentProject ManagementTechnology CommercializationTissue BiomechanicsBiomaterialsComputational ModelingFluid MechanicsStrategic PlanningStress/Fatigue Analysis

### **EDUCATION**

**CORNELL UNIVERSITY**, College of Engineering, Ithaca, NY

May 2010

Master of Engineering in Biomedical Engineering.

GPA: 3.6/4.0

Concentration: Biomedical Mechanics and Biomaterials

• Awarded the 2009 Martin McVoy scholarship for academic excellence

**JOHNS HOPKINS UNIVERSITY**, College of Engineering, Baltimore, MD Dec 2008

**Bachelor of Science in Chemical and Biomolecular Engineering.** GPA: 3.0/4.0

Concentration: Interfaces and Micro/Nanotechnology

Minor in Entrepreneurship and Management

Concentration: Technology Commercialization

• Awarded the 2008-09 and 2009-10 Technology Fellowship Grants

### **EXPERIENCE**

Lead Researcher/Engineer; Dr. Butcher Cardiovascular Developmental Lab

August 2009 – August 2010

- Biomedical Engineering Dept., Cornell University, Ithaca, NY
  - Designed and developed a novel bioreactor to culture, condition, and test tricuspid prosthetic heart valves; manufactured several prototypes and plan to patent
  - Saved significant time (~6 months) and money on development/testing via rapid prototyping and computational modeling
  - Developed anatomically accurate, cell-seeded hydrogel replacement heart valves
  - Observed several aortic heart valve replacement and coronary stent procedures at Guthrie Hospital

# Lead Researcher/Engineer; Dr. Gracias Biomedical Microtechnology Lab

March 2007 – May 2009

Chemical/Biomolecular Engineering Dept., Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD

• Designed novel drug delivery containers and was lead author of the scientific paper "Hierarchical Self-Assembly of Complex Polyhedral Microcontainers", published in the Journal of Micromechanics and Microengineering

## 3D Biomedical/Microtechnology Animator

April 2007 – May 2009

Institute for NanoBioTechnology (INBT), Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD

• Created professional animations of several biomedical-related research projects; Animations were aired on the Discovery Channel, published in a scientific text, published on YouTube (11,000+ views), and won numerous awards

# **Electronic Device Salesman**

August 2010 - Present

PC Richard & Son, Newington, CT

• Ranked #2 (Nov, Feb), #3 (Dec), and #5 (Oct, Jan) in sales out of ~30 employees; #1 in multiple focus sales categories

## **Engineering Lab Instructor**

January 2010 – May 2010

Chemical Engineering/Chemistry Depts., Cornell University, Ithaca, NY

• Led discussions, facilitated collaboration, troubleshoot problems, provided expertise; Responsible for 45 students

#### RELATED COURSEWORK

- <u>Technology Commercialization Project (JHU):</u> Mock commercialized and wrote an extensive technology assessment report on a novel robotic surgery technology; Worked closely with surgeons, computer scientists, and engineers at JHU
- Biomaterials Report (CU): Wrote a review/assessment report on Medtronic Mosaic® heart valve biomaterials
- <u>Senior Product Design project (JHU)</u>: Invented, designed, and mock marketed a novel hyperbaric oxygen therapy system to relieve symptoms of altitude illness; featured product in JHU Engineering Magazine

## TECHNICAL SKILLS

- <u>Computing/Modeling</u>: Fluid-Structure Interaction modeling, Finite Element Analysis, Stress Analysis, Fatigue Analysis, and 3D Modeling; experienced with SolidWorks, Comsol, Fluent, 3ds Max, AutoCAD, MS Project
- Laboratory: Cleanroom operation, SEM imaging, knowledge in TEM/AFM imaging, CT scanning